8th of May, 1945.
At last, [music] the darkness was
lifted. The people celebrated victory
over Nazi Germany.
From the D-Day landings on the beaches
of Normandy in June 1944,
it took the allies almost a full year to
win the war.
11 long months of fierce, often cruel
combat to plant the red flag on the roof
of the Reichstag.
11 months of hopes and fears.
11 interminable months to defeat a Reich
which had promised to endure for a
thousand years.
Those 11 months, with the highest death
toll of the war, left an eternal [music]
scar in hearts and on history.
Devastated, occupied, and humiliated
after five years of war with Germany,
Europe was still awaiting liberation.
In the summer of 1944, the allies were
raising hopes. On the western front, the
Normandy landings had been a success.
At the same time, on the eastern front,
Stalin was launching his huge army.
The Reich was finally caught in a pincer
movement.
But nothing was yet won. In September,
Hitler took the Allies by surprise with
a terrible counterattack in the
Ardennes.
It failed, but tens of thousands would
pay with their lives.
The Allies were worried.
And Hitler swore he would fight to the
bitter end.
In the new year of 1945, Hitler launched
Operation Northwind.
He used every plane at his disposal in
an attempt to annihilate the Allied Air
Force that had defeated him in the
Ardennes.
But the Anglo-Americans won this aerial
battle.
The Germans were unsettled to learn of
this fresh defeat.
But Hitler, with his exultant style,
convinced them to dig in.
>> [music]
>> One German woman wrote, "For the last
months of the war, I had to fight back
my tears each time I heard Hitler's
voice on the radio.
>> [music]
>> We didn't want to recognize the signs,
which were ever clearer, announcing the
impending downfall.
In our hearts, we [music] were afraid of
the terrible truth."
>> To boost the morale of the population,
Goebbels planned the premiere of a
feature film, Kolberg.
It was a film he had commissioned 2
years earlier.
This mega production told how the
Prussian troops repulsed the attacks of
Napoleon's armies.
After one screening, Goebbels noted,
"Kolberg is finally finished. The German
people are going to need it."
Meanwhile, to the east, the Red Army
took back the initiative.
Fresh supplies had reached the troops
massed along the Vistula.
But this concentration had not gone
unnoticed.
In Germany, General Guderian sounded the
alarm.
He implored Hitler to regroup his troops
on the Eastern Front to counter a Soviet
attack.
But Hitler would have none of it,
scoffing at the supposed threat. "It's
the biggest bluff since Genghis Khan.
Who came up with this idiocy?"
Even Himmler refused to admit it. "You
see, General, I don't think the Russians
are going to attack."
General Guderian tried desperately to
convince his superiors. Hitler repeated,
"This intelligence is completely
idiotic. Whoever wrote it should be shut
up in a lunatic asylum."
Deaf to all counsel, it was Hitler who
gradually shut himself into his own
world.
As Guderian had predicted, on the 12th
of January, 1945,
first Konev, then Zhukov, sent their
armies across the Vistula.
Endless columns of T-34 tanks advanced
along a front of more than 600 km
stretching from the shores of the Baltic
to the heart of Poland.
It was a devastating attack. The Russian
steamroller was back in motion.
The gunfire was so loud that even Zhukov
had to cover his ears.
For Stalin, this offensive was of
capital importance. In a few weeks, he
was due to meet Churchill and Roosevelt
in Yalta. He didn't want Poland to slip
out of his hands.
On the 17th of January 1945, 5 months
after the start of the insurrection, the
Red Army entered the Polish capital.
They found a ghost town.
As Stalin had calculated, there was no
one left to contest the authority of the
new occupying force.
The Polish communists had no trouble
taking over the reins.
The Soviets paraded in the capital to
celebrate a victory that came a bit too
late.
Having liberated the Polish capital on
the 27th of January 1945, the Soviets
discovered the Reich's biggest secret. A
camp the size of a town surrounded by
barbed wire.
Auschwitz-Birkenau.
The camp had been evacuated by the SS a
few days beforehand. All the guards had
fled.
The Soviets found 7,000 deportees
abandoned there.
7,000 survivors [music] for 1 and 1/2
million people murdered.
Before they left, the Nazis had tried to
erase evidence of their crimes.
They blew up the gas chambers and the
crematoriums.
But these factories of death
>> [music]
>> also formed the center of a system of
plunder.
The Soviets found hundreds of thousands
of pieces of clothing and hundreds of
thousands of shoes.
In a shed, they discovered 7 tons of
hair.
The deportees were not jubilant enough
in front of the cameras.
So the Soviets decided to re-stage the
liberation of the camp a few days later
using somewhat resuscitated deportees
and some local inhabitants.
>> The film would never be shown.
It no doubt revealed too much of the
reality.
In January 1945, around 100 camps were
still active across the Reich.
Even in their downfall, the destruction
of Europe's Jews remained a primary
objective for the Nazis.
For the allies, the liberation of these
killing grounds was not a priority.
Especially since the accounts given by
journalists [music] were so staggering
that those in the West refused to
believe them.
When the British reporter Alexander
Werth entered the camps of Majdanek and
Treblinka in July '44, he immediately
wrote an article on how these death
machines worked.
The sorting, the gas chambers, the
crematoriums, the bones ground as
fertilizer for the adjacent cabbage
fields.
But the BBC did not broadcast his
report. And the New York Herald Tribune
wrote, "We'd better await confirmation
of the horrors we're hearing about from
Lublin.
Despite everything we know of the Nazis'
savagery, these doings appear
unthinkable."
The camps were not the only theater of
Nazi crimes. [music]
And yet every town liberated by the Red
Army hid mass graves.
In the basement [music] of this
building, a laboratory performed
pseudo-medical experiments.
To the Nazis, the Jews, the Poles were
nothing more than slaves or fertilizer.
>> In 15 days, Zhukov and his men had
covered 400 km. No one in the Nazi
leadership had anticipated such a rapid
advance.
General Guderian wrote,
"The Russian tidal wave is taking on
utterly disastrous proportions for us."
And yet, the Germans continued to fight,
mainly because they were afraid.
The Red Army had shown some particularly
barbaric behavior. Neighborhoods and
villages were sometimes torched.
Stalin's army [music] plundered
shamelessly in this land of plenty.
Radios, saucepans, watches.
One soldier wrote,
"The Germans abandon everything, and our
men have invaded the houses.
Everything is in flames. Down from
pillows and feathers from mattresses are
flying everywhere.
Everyone from the foot soldier to the
colonel is carrying away his plunder.
This town has been crucified.
The Germans are right to flee [music]
from us like the plague."
Anyone suspected of being a Nazi could
be shot.
Almost 100,000 [music]
Germans were summarily executed.
One Soviet soldier noted, "The German
mother should curse the day she gave
birth to a son.
The Germans are now going to see the
horrors of war. Let them experience what
they wanted to inflict on others.
In Eastern Prussia, the Soviets briefly
occupied [music] the town of
Nemmersdorf.
The inhabitants were massacred. An orgy
of violence was unleashed.
Several women were said to have been
crucified naked on barn doors.
The Red Army was responding to the
magnitude of the crimes committed by the
Nazis. Millions of prisoners of war who
died of hunger, millions of civilians
murdered. The camps of Majdanek,
Auschwitz, and Treblinka had been
exposed.
Having lost 20 million of their own, the
Soviets were burning with vengeance.
The Soviet propagandist, Ilya Ehrenburg,
had for months been urging in the Red
Star newspaper,
"If you haven't killed a German each
day, your day has been wasted. Kill the
Germans. That's what your old mother
asks of you. The children are imploring.
Kill the Germans. That's what your
homeland demands of you.
The divisions and armies are not
advancing alone on Berlin. With them,
there are the trenches, the mass graves,
the ravines filled with the bodies of
the innocent, the cabbage fields of
Majdanek, and the trees of Idepsk, where
the Germans hanged so many unfortunates.
The boots, the little shoes and slippers
of the little children murdered in
Majdanek, walk alongside them to
Berlin."
The Red Army became experts in nurturing
hatred. And in its path, the enemy's
womenfolk were particularly targeted.
Rape became a weapon of war.
One young Soviet officer recalled,
"Women, mothers, and their children were
lying on both sides of the road, and
before each of them was a noisy gaggle
of men, their trousers down.
And our men shot those women who tried
[music] to save their children.
Smiling officers stood by, making sure
each soldier,
>> [music]
>> with no exceptions, took part.
Stalin, in person, excused these crimes.
[music] He declared,
"Imagine a man who fought from
Stalingrad to Belgrade, who has seen his
homeland devastated over thousands of
kilometers.
After all, what's the harm if he has a
bit of fun with some women after all the
horrors he has suffered?"
Vasily Grossman saw the terror in the
eyes of the women and young girls.
Horrible things happened to the German
women.
Across the whole German territory, close
to 2 million women are thought to have
been raped,
>> [music]
>> including wives and daughters of
communists.
After hesitating for a time, the Nazi
regime publicized these exactions.
>> Yeah.
>> The advance of the Soviet troops spread
panic among the civilians.
Hundreds of thousands of Germans took to
the road in the midst of a particularly
harsh winter.
"I'm going to try and reach your place."
wrote one young woman to her mother.
"Please, Mama, stay calm, but I won't
have Gabby with me. I could no longer
carry her, and she died."
"I couldn't go any further,
so I wrapped her up well, and I buried
her deep in the snow.
Gabby is not alone there. Thousands of
mothers were walking with their
children, and like me, they buried their
dead in the snow."
To escape, thousands of terrified men
and women swamped the stations and
ports.
In January '45, nearly 7,000 of them
packed onto the Wilhelm Gustloff.
It was sunk by a Soviet submarine.
More than 5,000 people disappeared
beneath the waves, three times more than
were lost on the Titanic.
On the 29th of January 1945, 4 million
Germans, 8.5 million according to some
estimates, were displaced.
At the end of January, between 40 and
50,000 people were arriving every day in
Berlin.
While refugees clogged the roads of
Germany, the Soviet troops who started
out from the Vistula stopped about 80 km
[music]
from Berlin on the banks of the Oder.
Zhukov's offensive had been a success.
In total, the Germans had lost [music]
450,000
men.
Having conquered most of Poland and
imposed his domination on the Balkans,
Stalin went into the Yalta Conference in
a position of strength.
Neither President Roosevelt, who was
weakened by sickness, nor the British
Prime Minister Winston Churchill, whose
country was drained after 5 years of
war, could stand up to him.
The Big Three agreed to divide Germany
into four occupied zones. Churchill
obtained a zone for France. This was not
out of the goodness of his heart.
Roosevelt had said that US troops would
pull out of Europe as soon as possible,
and Churchill didn't want to find
himself alone in the cage with the
Soviet bear.
Poland was handed to the communists,
although Stalin had vaguely promised to
organize free elections.
To the west, there was one last hurdle
to cross, the last natural barrier in
Germany, the Rhine.
All the bridges had been dynamited by
the Germans. General Montgomery was
still hoping to be first to cross the
river.
But the Americans beat him to it.
An advanced unit of the First US Army
found a bridge still standing at
Remagen, near Bonn.
The Germans had rigged it with
explosives, but had not yet detonated
them.
The Americans immediately established a
bridgehead on the eastern bank of the
river.
Hitler was furious and ordered the
engineers whose charges had not exploded
to be shot.
Meanwhile, Patton had sent his troops
across further south at Oppenheim
without notifying his superiors.
He was already spreading panic in German
territory.
Monty had dreamed of being first into
Germany. In fact, he was last.
But it was he who led the biggest
offensive.
He was in command of 1 and 1/4 million
soldiers.
This time, the lessons of Arnhem had
been learned.
The drop zones for the parachutists were
spot-on.
British troops pushed deep into Germany
and captured increasingly younger
soldiers.
The French also wanted to take part in
the action.
De Gaulle knew that France's place in
the victors' camp depended on its
participation in the Allied war effort.
He summoned De Lattre, chief of the
First Army.
You have to cross the Rhine, even if the
Americans don't grant you passage and
you have to go by boat. It's a matter of
the highest national importance.
Further south, the French forces under
General De Lattre also advanced. They
fought on German soil alongside the
Americans.
For the Allies, there was now a gaping
breach. They could finally invade the
Reich.
This was good news for them, but not for
Stalin.
As soon as he heard, he ordered Zhukov
to take Berlin as soon as possible to
avoid the Americans beating him to it.
Once the Rhine had been crossed, German
resistance founded.
Hitler had chosen to concentrate his
forces to the east.
He had exhausted his already diminished
reserves in the costly Battle of the
Ardennes.
Now some towns, rather than fighting to
the bitter end, were flying the white
flag.
The Anglo-Americans were making up
ground.
Churchill continually spurred on the
Americans.
>> [music]
>> "We have to push on and shake the
Russians' hands as far to the east as
possible," he urged.
But Berlin was in the future Soviet
occupation zone defined at Yalta.
Even if the Americans did take the city,
they would have had to later withdraw.
American public opinion would not accept
the 100,000 dead that this might have
cost simply as a matter of prestige.
Such humanitarian issues never hindered
Stalin.
So Eisenhower decided not to launch an
assault on Berlin.
His troops could even afford a break for
some home-style R&R.
Marlene Dietrich paid them a little
visit.
>> Hello, darling.
I want to say that sharing this
entertainment with you today is to me
more important than doing the
entertaining.
I'm certain that we can look forward to
a speedy victory.
Goodbye. Good luck.
Godspeed.
>> But Ike's armies did not down their
weapons for long. To defeat Nazi Germany
swiftly without too heavy losses in
their ranks, the Americans and British
pursued a merciless bombing campaign.
They relentlessly pounded German
industrial areas and annihilated cities
packed with civilians.
Their aim was to smash the Reich's
economic potential and to break the
morale of the population,
>> [music]
>> thereby undermining the regime.
Between January and April 1945, 471,000
tons of bombs were dropped on Germany.
Cologne, Hamburg, and Berlin were all
hit.
>> Well, men, now that we've been the first
ones to Berlin, how would you like to go
back again?
>> [screaming]
>> In mid-February, Churchill wanted to
bombard the city of Dresden as a show of
strength to the Soviets, who had been
less than dazzled by Montgomery's
performance. The city was consumed in a
firestorm.
In under 24 hours, more than 25,000
inhabitants perished.
>> [music]
[music]
>> A city with no war-related industry and
of no strategic importance,
>> [music]
>> nothing justified the allies' brutal
attack.
But destroying Dresden also meant
driving up the number of refugees and
perturbing the movements of the
Wehrmacht.
>> [music]
>> The Allied leaders may have felt some
regret over Dresden, but not for long,
because Hitler's [music] obstinacy drove
them to maintain the bombing campaign,
whatever the cost for the civilian
population.
>> [music]
>> At the end of March 1945, the Reich
slipped into chaos. The outcome of the
war was no longer in any doubt.
A German officer noted in his diary, "We
are reaching the end.
>> [music]
>> Do our leaders have any exit strategy in
mind? The death of our soldiers, the
destruction of our towns and villages,
is there any sense to this now?"
Another wrote,
"Is there no one there to overpower
[music]
the madman and call for an end to this?
Are they still generals? No, they are
trash, wet rags, they are cowards."
But these words of revolt remained
confined to private diaries. After
writing these lines, those young
soldiers returned to the combat.
And yet, German society could not manage
to rise up. And as a result, it
continued its plunge to new depths.
The regime launched a new phase,
radicalization against the Germans
themselves.
Whoever was not prepared to fight would
face execution.
In Königsberg, 80 deserters were
executed.
Often, victims' bodies were left at the
roadside with a sign,
"I'm a deserter and I refused to protect
German women and children."
Villages displaying the white flag were
threatened with destruction.
But this radicalization was even more
harsh on deportees.
The progression of the Anglo-American
armies to the west and the Soviets to
the east led Himmler to close the camps,
sending the deportees on abominable
death marches.
The detainees were on the road, but not
getting anywhere. [music]
The Nazis no longer had time to gas
people, so they exterminated through
cold and hunger.
Those who could not keep up the pace of
the march got a bullet to the head.
When the Allies liberated the camps,
they found most of them almost entirely
empty.
The Germans had only left certain
deportees considered too weak to be
evacuated.
In April 1945, the British entered
Bergen-Belsen.
They found 30,000 [music] prisoners
hovering between life and death.
Some 10,000 bodies lay around rotting.
It was an apocalyptic vision for the
liberators.
British troops had to use bulldozers to
shift the thousands of bodies to avoid
epidemics. [music]
The same month,
the Americans entered the order of
concentration camp,
an offshoot of Buchenwald.
Eisenhower was overwhelmed.
"I've never had such a shock in my
entire life," he confessed.
Patton was physically sick near a shed.
Eisenhower ordered the population of the
next door town to visit the camp.
In front of a crematorium
where they burned 200 bodies per day,
women fainted.
Nonetheless, the officers insisted
[music] that the Germans confront the
horrors which they had allowed to
happen.
On a table stood lampshades [music] made
of human skin.
There were tattooed skins that a camp
official had collected [music]
and shrunken heads.
Trophies of Nazi [music] barbarity.
Discovering these horrors, one
journalist wrote,
"The gates of hell had opened."
Other camps were liberated, and more
visits were imposed on local
populations.
Eisenhower declared,
"People tell us that the American
soldier doesn't know why he's fighting.
Now at least he knows against who he's
fighting."
The discovery of the hell of the
concentration camps was a shock for the
whole world.
For 10 months, the Reich had been
shrinking.
In April, the final act began.
Berlin, the last citadel, was preparing
for for ultimate battle.
On the 12th of April, 1945, the Berlin
Philharmonic Orchestra performed
Wagner's Götterdämmerung.
To make up for the lack of personnel, an
army of children, women, and the
elderly, marshaled by several thousand
SS fanatics, had to defend the capital.
They set up obstacles.
Goebbels did a good job, and all those
defending the city had a smile in these
[music] propaganda images.
>> [music]
>> To set ambushes, every German was
equipped with a rifle or a panzerfaust,
an anti-tank weapon.
The factories had turned out more than 3
million of them in recent months.
In the streets of Berlin, people were
given fast-track training.
>> Many Germans still had faith in the
Reich.
One young soldier wrote to his parents,
"I simply can't believe that the Führer
would sacrifice us dumbly. No one can
strip me of my faith in him. He is
everything to me."
Certain officers confiscated white
handkerchiefs to stop the defenders
using them to surrender.
Nazi dignitaries still believed,
especially since on the same day in the
United States on the 12th of April,
1945, President Roosevelt died.
Hitler rejoiced. "The great miracle, the
one I always predicted, has happened.
The war is not lost."
Hitler was blinded [music] by his own
illusions.
But, the hope did not last long because
the Red Army was closing in on the
capital.
Around a model of Berlin, Soviet
generals discussed the plan of attack.
Supplies from the east had finally
arrived on the banks of the Oder.
Tanks, shells, planes, 30,000 cannons.
On the 16th of April, the biggest
artillery barrage of the war commenced.
1,236,000
shells were fired.
100,000 tons of steel rained down on the
Germans.
2 million men moved on Berlin.
Stalin encouraged rivalry between his
generals. "Whoever breaks through first
can take Berlin," he declared.
Zhukov made a direct thrust, but came up
against stiff resistance.
Konev went round the city to the south.
The 196 Soviet [music] divisions
attacked from every side.
The Russians had one objective, the
Chancellery, under which Hitler's bunker
was located.
Zhukov moved forward, [music]
but for every German killed, three
Russians fell.
Stalin wanted to see Berlin totally
encircled to avoid the Anglo-Americans
profiting from a sudden German collapse
and entering the capital first.
In Berlin, the ground itself shook.
Each crossroads was defended, sometimes
by young children.
Hitler sheltered in his bunker.
In these last pictures of the dictator,
filmed 1 month earlier, the censor
[music] cut a piece of film which has
never been shown.
In it, one can see the Führer trembling,
incapable of controlling himself.
Hitler is no more than a shadow.
And yet, at no point was there any
question of surrender.
Goebbels blustered and made out all was
well.
"The situation is turning to our
advantage. The Americans are marching on
Berlin. The big turnaround is underway.
We have to hold the city at any cost."
Another lie from the Minister of
Propaganda, [music] but then that was
his job after all. And yet, 110 km away,
on the 25th of April in Torgau,
the long-awaited day finally came.
The Reich was cut in two.
The Soviet and American armies met up.
While for the leadership, this was a
time to be wary, for the ordinary
soldier, it was a time of celebration.
That said, certain Soviet soldiers
avoided excessive fraternization that
might have sent [music] them to the
gulag.
In Berlin, 2 million civilians were
caught in in trap.
It was now a matter of survival.
Here and there a horse was cut up.
However mighty the Soviet artillery
power had been, even in a mechanized war
it is the infantry who have to finish
the job.
Street by street, cellar by cellar.
In these last days, the motivation of
the Germans changed.
They were no longer fighting for their
great Reich, for the Führer, or for
National Socialism, but to save their
skins.
The Russians were closing in on the
bunker where Hitler was still
positioning imaginary armies.
The elites had fled the city.
When Goebbels realized all was lost, he
wondered,
"What's to be done with a people whose
men don't even fight when their women
are being raped? All the plans, all the
ideas of National Socialism are too
elevated, too noble for such a people.
These folk deserve the fate they are
about to meet."
At the same time in Italy, on the 28th
of April, Mussolini was captured while
trying to escape.
He was shot.
His body and that of his mistress were
abused by the crowd.
When Hitler learned of the death of Il
Duce, he concluded,
"Dead or alive, I don't want to fall
into the hands of the enemy. After my
death, my body is to be burned and no
one will be able to find it."
On the 30th of April, deep in his
bunker, Hitler committed suicide along
with his wife, Eva Braun.
His body was then burned by his
chauffeur using 200 L of gas.
For 12 years, the dictator had ruled
over Germany.
He had dreamed of a thousand-year Reich.
This mirage disappeared in the ruins of
his capital.
One last lie. The radio claimed that
Hitler had died leading the heroic
defenders of Berlin.
The same day, [music]
Zhukov's troops broke through.
His soldiers seized the Reichstag.
Vasily Grossman wrote,
>> [music]
>> "I wanted to shout, to call to all our
brother fighters who lay in Russian,
Ukrainian, Belorussian, and Polish soil,
who were sleeping the eternal slumber on
the field of honor. Comrades, can you
hear us? We made it."
Two days later, the Russians
reconstructed the scene. A photo was
taken.
But this historic picture had to be
retouched because one detail had been
overlooked. One of the soldiers was
wearing several watches on his wrists.
But where was Hitler? This question
haunted the Russians. Soviet soldiers
found a body which bore a strong
resemblance.
But it turned out they were
photographing themselves next to a
doppelganger.
A A of specialists was sent by Stalin to
investigate.
They found the charred bodies of
Goebbels and his wife
alongside with the lifeless bodies of
their six children.
A few months earlier, they were still
being used for party propaganda.
Their parents had murdered them before
committing suicide.
Hitler's remains were finally discovered
[music] in a bomb crater.
When he learned of the Fuhrer's demise,
Stalin exclaimed,
"That's the end of that bastard. A shame
we didn't take him alive."
The remains were secretly shipped to
Russia.
Even Zhukov, who savored his victory and
paid a visit to the beast's lair, knew
nothing of this epilogue.
With Hitler dead, capitulation became
possible for his successors.
On the 7th of May, in a modest school in
Reims at the headquarters of Allied
Forces, the German representatives
accepted the terms of an unconditional
surrender.
After the signing, General Jodl had the
temerity to [music] stand up and
declare, "The German army is now in the
hands of the Allies. I hope that the
victor will treat us with generosity."
With the pens used for the signatures,
Ike made the V for victory.
>> In January 1943
late President Roosevelt and Mr.
Churchill
met in Casablanca.
They all there pronounced the formula of
unconditional surrender for the Axis
power.
In Europe
that formula has now been fulfilled.
>> But these images were not yet shown
because Stalin was not satisfied with
this capitulation.
The strongman of the Kremlin bemoaned,
"It was the Soviet people who bore on
their shoulders most of the weight of
the war."
Stalin demanded that a second surrender
be signed the following day in Berlin.
On the 8th of May, the American, French,
German, and British delegations crossed
the shattered city.
In Zhukov's headquarters on the edge of
Berlin, they awaited the arrival of
Field [music] Marshal Keitel.
When he entered, no one replied [music]
to his salute.
The various delegations signed all
[music] five acts of surrender.
General de Lattre signed for France.
It was 11:00 p.m. on the 8th of May, but
it was already 1:00 a.m. in Moscow.
The Soviets noted the date as the 9th of
May.
But the surrender [music] did not bring
an end to the tragedy.
The halt in hostilities was followed by
a wave of suicides.
Besides the high command like Himmler,
many thousands of [music] anonymous
Germans killed themselves, sometimes
with their families, for fear of the
Soviets, or else to follow Hitler to the
afterlife.
In 1935, Hitler had promised the
Germans, "Give me 10 years and you won't
recognize [music] Germany."
He kept his word.
>> [cheering]
>> "It's over. It's over." That was the cry
that could be heard in towns around the
world as they celebrated victory.
>> [applause and cheering]
>> The people hailed the liberation they
had waited so long for.
>> [cheering]
>> But the joy was also [music] tinged with
gravity.
The dark shadow of Nazism would not be
erased in a day.
The suffering endured had left an
indelible scar on memories.
Nazism had plumbed the depths of horror.
The extermination of the Jews, the
massacres of civilians, the torture of
resistance members would forever haunt
the conscience of humanity.
Yet, a continent [music] had to get back
on its feet. The ruined towns had to be
rebuilt. The million of displaced
persons had to return to home.
These were the huge challenges of the
post-war period.
From this chaos caused by the Nazi
order, a new era would nonetheless
emerge.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So
>> [music]